<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A second answer to Thomas Moore, to that which he calls, his Defence against the poyson, &amp;c. Wherein is shewed the crooked wayes, the Serpent is forced to take to keep God and his creatures at a distance, and yet would do it under the name of a teacher. But is seen to be the same, that perswaded man out from his guide in spirit, and now would keep him so, lest his unclean wayes in the heart of man should be discovered with the spiritual light of Christ; and so man should turn to the Lord, who is that spirit, and the vail be done away, ... Here is also 54. lies gathered out from amongst a multitude more, with T.M. hath heaped up for his defence, against the truth, which he calles the poyson of Satan, which are sent him back to the 48. that I sent him before, that he may either prove them, or they root with the founder, for the truth they touch not. / Set forth to clear the truth from this froth, cast upon it by the enemy thereof, By a friend to the seed of truth, called James Naylor.</title>
            <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89851</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N314</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E868_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202991</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863103</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863103</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115285</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89851)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115285)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 131:E868[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A second answer to Thomas Moore, to that which he calls, his Defence against the poyson, &amp;c. Wherein is shewed the crooked wayes, the Serpent is forced to take to keep God and his creatures at a distance, and yet would do it under the name of a teacher. But is seen to be the same, that perswaded man out from his guide in spirit, and now would keep him so, lest his unclean wayes in the heart of man should be discovered with the spiritual light of Christ; and so man should turn to the Lord, who is that spirit, and the vail be done away, ... Here is also 54. lies gathered out from amongst a multitude more, with T.M. hath heaped up for his defence, against the truth, which he calles the poyson of Satan, which are sent him back to the 48. that I sent him before, that he may either prove them, or they root with the founder, for the truth they touch not. / Set forth to clear the truth from this froth, cast upon it by the enemy thereof, By a friend to the seed of truth, called James Naylor.</title>
                  <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30, 29-35, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, at the Black-spread-Eagle at the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655 [i.e. 1656]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Moore, Thomas.  A defence against the poyson of Satan's designe.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb: 17".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Moore, Thomas, --  Junior. --  Defence against the poyson of Satan's designe --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:115285:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
A SECOND ANSWER TO Thomas Moore, To that which he calls, his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence againſt the poyſon, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Wherein is ſhewed the crooked wayes, the Serpent is forced to take to keep God and his Creatures at a diſtance, and yet would do it under the name of a Teacher.</p>
            <p>But is ſeen to be the ſame, that perſwaded man out from his guide in ſpirit, and now would keep him ſo, leſt his unclean wayes in the heart of man ſhould be diſcovered with the ſpiritual Light of Chriſt; and ſo man ſhould turn to the Lord, who is that ſpirit, and the vail be done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, which is come over the heart by looking out; &amp; ſo man ſhould come to ſee his Maker, to be his leader in ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Here is alſo 54. lies gathered out from amongſt a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude more, with <hi>T. M.</hi> hath heaped up for his Defence, againſt the truth, which he calles the poyſon of Satan, which are ſent him back to the 48. that I ſent him before, that he may either prove them, or they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oot with the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for the truth they touch not.</p>
            <p>Set forth to clear the truth from this froth, caſt upon it by the enemy thereof.</p>
            <p>By a friend to the ſeed of truth, called <hi>James Naylor.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Bleſſed are you when men ſhall perſecute you, and ſay all manner of evill on you falſely for my names ſake: for ſo have they done to the Prophets and Apoſtles before you.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles calvert,</hi> at the <hi>Black-ſpread-Eagle</hi> at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:115285:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> Thou art deſired to take notice of theſe faults in the Printing, and correct them with thy Pen.</p>
            <p>PAge 2. 1. 17. ſor <hi>filthy,</hi> read <hi>frothy.</hi> P. 9. 1. 3a. for <hi>Antepage,</hi> r. <hi>Antidote, page</hi> P. 10. l. 18. for <hi>for, r. ſo.</hi> P. 11. <hi>for you know,</hi> r. <hi>I know.</hi> P. 12. 1. 2, 3. for, <hi>God was not, God is manifeſt,</hi> &amp;c. r. <hi>God was, not, God is manifeſt,</hi> &amp;c. P. 16. 1. 26. for, <hi>rendring to us to all.</hi> r. <hi>rendring us to all.</hi> P. 17. 1. 2. for. <hi>would have to have us liberty,</hi> r. <hi>would have us to have liberty.</hi> P. 18. 1. 6. for, <hi>John Frey,</hi> r. <hi>John Wrey.</hi> P. 19. 1. 3. for, <hi>ſlain in him,</hi> r. <hi>ſlain in Chriſt.</hi> P. 21. 1. 5. for <hi>ſince,</hi> r. <hi>ſence.</hi> P. 22. 1. 19. for, <hi>angred,</hi> r. <hi>any read.</hi> P. 24. 1. 6. for, <hi>I anſwer,</hi> r. <hi>I anſwered.</hi> P. 27. 1. 8. for, <hi>ſeal,</hi> r. <hi>deal.</hi> P. 29. 1. 10. for, <hi>being uged,</hi> r. <hi>being judged.</hi> P. 30. 1. 27. for <hi>nad,</hi> r. <hi>and.</hi> P. 32. 1. 7. for <hi>trade,</hi> r. <hi>tread.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115285:2"/>
            <head>A Second Anſwer to <hi>Thomas Moore.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>THomas Moore,</hi> when wilt thou love the truth, and ceaſe thy deceit, and minde the light of Chriſt, to lead thee out of thy crooked paths, that the mouth of the Serpent may be ſtopt, that belcheth out thy own ſhame in thy lies and confuſions, as thou haſt done; not onely when I was with thee before many witneſſes, but alſo in the ethy two Books, wherein thy lies are too many to number: In thy firſt Book, I ſent thee back 48. lies, out of three times as many more, that thou might prove them; But inſtead thereof, thou adds heaps upon heaps; and ſo it muſt be, that he may be revealed, who abides not in the truth; and ſo is a lyer from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and ſo thou art found. As thou didſt make up the ſubſtance of thy firſt Book with lies, ſo thou begins this. And in the front of thy lye, thou makes a cover for it, leaſt it ſhould be ſeen. In thy firſt Book thou ſayes, thou ſhalt refuſe further to meddle, or have to do with me, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe thou perceive in me ſome turn to the Lord; And in thy ſecond Book, thou renders me as the mouth of the Devill, to caſt out his poyſon: Is this the turn to the Lord thou perceives in me? Orthou would have me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that in this Book (thou haſt thus filled with deceit to caſt upon me) thou doſt not meddle with me therein: This by the way, all may ſee thou art no bungler in that Art; for in the moſt part of thy lies thou makes ſure. ſo to preſent them, as to leave open a way or two to eſcape, if thou be taxt therewith; and if not, then let it paſſe for
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115285:3"/>
truth, and this all ſhall ſee in thy Books, who doth but read them with the light of truth: which deceipts, I ſhall not much trouble my ſelfe to trace thee in, onely in ſome few where the Serpent would devoure the ſimple by the way, and ſhut up the Kingdom againſt ſuch as deſire to chuſe the plain way, I ſhall diſcover thy ſpirit, of what na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it is, that they that will, may beware.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is three things thou would have the Reader to believe from thee, if any be ſo void of truth: Firſt, that I have belied thee, and the truth atteſted by thee; To which I ſay, 48. of thoſe thou calles thy truths, I ſent thee back again into thy bottle, beſides many more of the ſame nature I layed open. I knowing theſe to be notorious lies, atteſted by thee for truths, I could do no leſſe then teſtifie again them, Any other belying of thee, thou art not able to prove.</p>
            <p n="2">2. How empty, filthy, and corrupt my Anſwers is, and how plainly the Scriptures are wreſted by me: To which I ſay, to the firſt part; the boaſter ſpeaks the frothy words. To the ſecond I ſay, if quoting Scriptures, without ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or diminiſhing be no wreſting then thou haſt but herein added a lie more to the number.</p>
            <p n="3">3. How the Woolf appears in the Sheeps Skins, in the beginning, and cloſe of my Book. To which I ſay, My Book begins with diſcovering, thy lying Antichriſtian Doctrine leaſt by it the ſimple ſouls ſhould be deceived; and what I ſay, I make it appear to be truth, and my Book ends with twelve points of truth laid down, needful to be cleared to all from the Devills miſts caſt upon them, and this is no part of the Wolfs work; But what Beaſt was that which was up amongſt thee, and thy Companions, who when I ſpoke the truth amongſt you, your Weapon was heared up to knock me down in the yard, when you was on Horſeback, and left the diſpute the latter day, which in this Book thou wouldſt cover with a ſubtle lie. If I had intended ſuch a thing to any Creature, I could not have been excuſed in the ſight of God from a Wolf, or
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115285:3"/>
a Dogg; for I am ſure it was no part of a man, much leſſe of a Saint, to knock one in the head, who did not reſiſt, neither had any thing in his hand, wherewith to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt.</p>
            <p>For the firſt of theſe, and the deceiptful crooked wayes thou takes to excuſe thy lies and blaſphemies, who doth but read thy Books, and my Anſwer to thy firſt, needs not any further to ſee thee withall, if they minde but any light in them; yet for love to the ſimple ones, I ſhall lay thee open in ſome of them, that they may the better finde thee out in the reſt.</p>
            <p>In thy firſt, thou begins with, Thou ſayes thou doſt not gather thy charge againſt me, that I preach down the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and work of Chriſt in one body for us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> from my letter, becauſe I witneſſed the fleſh of Chriſt the food of the inner Man; But from my comparing my Confeſſion of the fleſh of Chriſt in me, with the Apoſtles preaching down Circumciſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Wherein all that ever reads my letter in thy book, may be witneſs againſt thee, if in any part of my letter I have compared theſe two together, nor ever did it enter into my heart ſo to do; But the end of my letter is this, to let you ſee your ſelves more blinde, as to the knowledge of the ſpirit, and its reaching and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation then the Jews was, as much as if I had ſaid, if you oppoſe my Teſtimony when I confeſſed the fleſh of Chriſt, which the letter doth declare of; what a Generation would you have been, had you lived in the time of the Apoſtles, who preached down Circumciſion, which the letter ſaid ſhould continue? So the compariſon ſtands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt your oppoſing the teſtimony of the ſpirit in me, which is according to the letter, and the Jews oppoſing the Apoſtles Teſtimony in ſpirit, which diſannulled the Letter, wherein you are found double to them in blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: Now how this preaches down the perſon of Chriſt, or whether I made that compariſon, thou ſayes I did let a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny judge, who all may ſee thou haſt made it thy ſelfe to ſlander withall, without the leaſt ground from me, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115285:4"/>
then ſayes, I made it. O thou ſhameleſſe man, how doſt thou bend thy tongue for lies and ſlanders?</p>
            <p>Alſo having, in thy book, called perfection, a deviliſh Doctrine, and being told of it, and confounded in it by Scripture: now thou covers it, as though thou call'd our Doctrine of perfection deviliſh, and ſayes, thou no where findes Chriſt gave gifts to perfect men in lying, &amp;c. I ſay, When didſt thou read of any other Doctrine of perfection preacht by us, but the Doctrine of Chriſt, and his Light and Spirit for perfecting the Saints; and this is it thou calleſt diveliſh; and for thy lies, our Doctrine layes thee open therein, elſe we ſhould not be ſo much oppoſed by the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and the Generation of lyers, who deny the light of truth within, as thou Child of darkneſs doſt, who ſayes, the grace of God that brings ſalvation to all men, inſtructs them not to look to any light, or ſpirit in them for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; herein ſhewing thy ſelfe wholly ignorant of the ſpirit of Chriſt and his light; for all who have the ſpirit of Chriſt, they have it within them, and his light in them, which thou denies for direction; and ſo art Antichriſt, oppoſing the ſpirituall light, and teaching, without which none can come to know God, or themſelves, and that is the cauſe of all thy lies thou haſt told in thy books; for, who denies the ſpirit of truth, which is appointed of God to lead into all truth, muſt needs be led with the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, who are ſenſuall, not having the ſpirit nor light in them; and if thou hadſt ſaid no more in thy books, this had been enough to have ſhewed thy ſelfe a blinde Guide, who denies the teachings of the ſpirit and light within, to be from the grace of God; for none can have the grace of God to appear with its light and teachings, and ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but within; for the grace of God is ſpirituall, and that which is ſpiritual is within, elſe no Creature can have it to ſalvation; wherefore Chriſt ſaith, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God is within you, Not lo here, lo there, (as you <note place="margin">Luk. 17: 20. 21. Rom, 10. 8</note> Phariſees would have it:) And ſaith he; Go not forth, and, the Apoſtles preached the word of Faith that was in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115285:4"/>
peoples hearts, to whom they preached, and they came to the knowledge of God, and his glory, by the light that <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 6. Col. 3. 16. Hob. 13. 9. Gal. 4. 6. Eph. 4. 18, 19.</note> ſhined in their hearts: and the Saints had their grace in their hearts, and the word of God dwelt in them richly; yea God himſelf dwelt in their hearts by his ſpirit; and yet thou ſayes the grace of God teaches not to look to any light within; and here thou art clearly manifeſt, to be heart-blind, and would have all in thy State; for herein your Kingdom would fall, and you could no longer raign over peoples Conſciences and Eſtates: if they come once to know Gods grace in their hearts, and the teachings of the ſpirit within them, they would ſoon ſee your Idoll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip, and high place-preaching to be out of both form and power, of that which the Saints liv'd in and practiſed, and no longer would they give their money for that which is no bread, and their labours for that which doth not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit; and then could you no longer ride upon the Nations <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.</note> as Maſters; and the Whore would fall: ſo thou, and the reſt do what you can, to keep people ſpiritually blind from looking within, that ſo they may come to you for teaching, and ſo be ever learning; but never able to come to the knowledge of the truth ever loadened with ſin, but never ſet free, being led out by you, and kept from enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in where freedom is; for the vail muſt be over the heart till they turn to the ſpirit: Now the Lord is that ſpirit; and where the ſpirit is, there is liberty from ſin, from glory to glory by the ſpirit, which no litteral Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration <note place="margin">Luk. 17. 20, 21. Iſa. 51. 7. Pſal, 119. 11. Jer. 20. 9. 2 Cor, 6. 16.</note> can ever come to, though the Letter be read every day, and ſo you deny both Letter and Spirit alſo; for ſaith the Letter you ſhall be all taught of God; and none can be taught of God but by the light of Chriſt within, in ſpirit; and thou that denies this, art againſt Chriſt, and his Kingdom is in the heart, and his Law in the heart, and his word in the heart, and he himſelf in the heart: therefore thou his enemy would not have his people to look there for teaching ſo let all who deſires to be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited unto Chriſt, avoid thee and thy Antichriſtian
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115285:5"/>
Doctrine, and it is no matter what thou ſayes, as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the things of God, who art heart-blinde, and haſt not thy teaching from the light and ſpirit of Chriſt-within thee. All that comes out muſt needs be of the Devill, and ſo it is in all, who hath it not from the light and ſpirit of Chriſt within them; for he that ſpeaks of himſelf is the lyer, and the Father of it, and ſo it is ſeen of thee in thy books; and alſo thy blaſphemy, who ſayes, to direct, to look to the light within, is the lame, as directing men to ſeek to a Familiar ſpirit; and of that brood thou art, who ever called Chriſt <hi>Beelzebub;</hi> and light, darkneſs. O thou blaſphemer! did Chriſt direct to a familiar ſpirit, when he told them, The Kingdom was within them, and <note place="margin">Luk. 17. 21 Luk. 11. 34, 35. 36.</note> that the light of the body is the eye, and if it be ſingle, the whole body is full of light, as the bright ſhining of a Candle doth give light: And, keep thy heart with all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, for from thence are the Iſſues of life: And ſaith, Thy word have I hid in my heart, that I might not ſin; and Commune with your own hearts, and be ſtill; and the Law of God is written in the heart, and the heart of the wiſe <note place="margin">Prov. 4. 23 Pſal. 119. 11. Pſal. 4. Heb. 8. 10. Prov. 16. 23. Joh. 16. 13</note> teacheth his mouth, and the ſpirit of truth is that which muſt lead into all truth: Nay doth not all the Scriptures teſtifie to the light and ſpirit-teaching within; and that they are none of Chriſts who have not the ſpirit of Chriſt, and is it counted a familiar ſpirit now with thee? Now is it ſeen to all the Children of the light, that Antichriſt is revealing, as the Scriptures hath foretold, and the Man of ſin pleading againſt freedom from ſin, and the blinde Guids preaching againſt the light, and he that is born of the fleſh againſt the ſpirit and its teachings, and the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of darkneſs againſt the light that manifeſts the evill deeds, and he is diſcovering who abode not in the truth, and the ſpirit and light is that truth which thou would preach down, to lead out into the world, where the lyer is, who hates the light becauſe his deeds are evill; And this is thy work in thy books, and to thy Maſter, and his work thou art faithful, uſing thy utmoſt ſubtlety to do his
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115285:5"/>
work thorowly, to preach Chriſt out of his Creatures, that none ſhould minde his light and ſpirit, but without in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other world, that ſo the Devill may have his will in the heart in this World, while any one lives, and ſerve God, and be made free when they are dead, and can do their Maſter no more ſervice, if they would; and when thou haſt ſtruck them off, from looking at any light or ſpirit within, then like the Serpent, leaſt his head ſhould be ſeen, thou hides thy ſelfe, with telling, of, Not to lean to their own underſtanding: and (ſayes thou) though the word be nigh them in their hearts, that it might be, yet it is not, received by them in their hearts, or dwelling there as a light or principle to direct them, while in their naturall eſtate, when thou haſt done what thou can to perſwade them, that the looking to it, is but as to a familiar ſpirit; But is that their own underſtanding, which condemns their natural underſtanding, as they are fallen from God, and lets them ſee, that all their underſtanding, wiſdom and prudence, is God hid from, and manifeſts all their deeds in that ſtate to be evill: this hath every natural man in him, from the Father of Spirits, which manifeſtation of ſpirit is given to every one to profit withall, if it be but minded, and not quenched; and without this can be no knowledge of God, and if this Candle be put out, there is no doing the work of God, till it be lighted, further then to wait; and there is no waiting, but with the heart in ſpirit, till it ſhine out of darkneſs again; and till then, all the Creature doth, is but deeds of darkneſs, and not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted by God; his prayers are abomination, and his plowing ſin; yea though all the world ſhould flatter ſuch a one, they could not ſave him nor unite him to God, nor give peace of Conſcience with God, nor Sealing in ſpirit; and this the Children of light know, though blinde Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents and deaf Adders oppoſe it, who walk in craſt and deceit; but the Apoſtles who handled not the word de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully, did commend themſelves to that in every mans <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 2.</note> Conſcience in the ſight of God: and the Miniſtration of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115285:6"/>
Chriſt, is to the ſpiritual ſeed, whereby the ſpiritual ſeed is quickned, and raiſed out of darkneſs and death; but the Miniſtration of the Hireling and falſe Prophet, is to the itching eares; and ſo the Beaſt and the falſe Prophet joynes againſt the ſeed of God, to keep it in death and darkneſs; and if it be born up, then they perſecute him in whom it is born, And theſe take the letter, there with to deny the light, and oppoſe that ſpirit that gave it forth, and whereof the letter reſtifies, becauſe they have not the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 5.</note> word abiding within them, and this was the work of the Phariſes and Hirelings; but never any one of Chriſts Miniſters denyed the light and ſpirit within as thou doſt, yet ſlaidly and covertly: ſo as if thou be taxt for it, thou may have an excuſe to come out of, and deny thy work with a meaning and conſequence; but if none diſproves thee, then goes on with thy work, to lead out ſimple people from the light of Chriſt in ſpirit, to follow thy I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations without, a ſpirit and light without, which thou never ſaw.</p>
            <p>Yet in this one thing, there is not many exceeds thee; for when ever thou layes down a deceit, the end whereof is to deny the light, or ſpirit, or perfection, or to ſlander any, who own the truth, in theſe things thou makes ſure before thou leave it to make two or three wayes for eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape, leaſt it fall upon thy head, knowing before the thing to be ſuch, thou cannot ſtand by with Scripture; and this the leaſt Child of Light may ſee in thy books, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall not much need to trace thee therein, the thing being ſo plainly evident to all, that in the light read thy books, and my anſwers thereto.</p>
            <p>And when thou haſt told a lie, and being told thereof, thou on purpoſe having left out a word or ſyllable, there thou makes an eſcape. As for inſtance, in thy anſwer to the laſt Query, which asks, What that grace of God is, which brings ſalvation, and hath appeared to all men: thy lie is, that indeed we believe no ſuch thing, as the grace of God appearing to men; which I finding this to be as anſwer
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115285:6"/>
to the Query, I tell thee, Thou anſwers with a ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſaying, that indeed we believe no ſuch thing, as the grace of God appearing to all men: now thou having left out the word all (for eſcape) which is in the Query, and in the Scripture alſo: In thy defence ſayes thou, my words are, They believe no ſuch thing, as the grace of God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing to men; and this thou would charge upon me, to be a lie, when the lie is thy own; and hath both abuſed the Query, and the Scripture, on which the Query is grounded, leaving out the word [all] to make it, and ſuch holes as this thou creeps out of, to hide the lyer from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeen.</p>
            <p>And in other places where thou haſt gone a crooked way to fetch a compaſſe to make a lie (for otherwiſe thou could not) which when I come to anſwer, and takes the ſum of the thing in brief, (which otherwiſe might fill a volume) then thy eſcape is, becauſe I tell not all the lying ſtory over again after thee; and in theſe and ſuch like crooked wayes, thou goes about to avoid the truth, and winde out thy head, leaſt it ſhould be bruiſed therewith: and this ſhall any ſee, who in the light doth but read thy books, and my anſwer; wherein I might trace thee into every particular, were it needful or dark to the leaſt ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity.</p>
            <p>Alſo in other places, where thy eſcape will not ſerve thee with a ſeeming ſhew of truth, before thou ſtick, thou wilt forge an abſolute lie. As for inſtance page 9. where thou mentioneſt my charging thee to ſay, that none have yet ceaſed from their own works: To which thou ſayes, thy Tayings are, that none here have yet ſo ceaſed from their own works, &amp;c. To prove which words, thou quotes Antepage 44. which all that read that page, ſhall read thee a lyer, thereby to accuſe the truth; for theſe words are not ſo there, nor any where elſe that I have yet ſeen; and ſo according to the Doctrine, to thee it is, who haſt not yet ceaſed from thy own works, who art yet a lyer, and covering one lie with another, carping at words,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115285:7"/>
when I ſpeak the ſence) to make me a lier, when thou canſt not hit thy own words; but he that is come to Chriſt is ceaſed from his own works, who is become Gods workmanſhip; but the Serpent hath no portion here, and ſo would exclude all others, who knowes no better but to believe him; but where God works all our work in us, he ordains peace there; and ſuch are entred into the Reſt, the Serpent knowes not, <hi>Iſay</hi> 26. 52. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 13. but they which did believe, were entred into reſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 3. but thy Sophiſtry is to keep people from looking for any reſt from their own works, till they be cut off by death, and can ſerve the Devil no longer, and ſo art one of thoſe who will neither enter thy ſelfe, nor ſuffer thoſe that would, like the reſt of thy Fathers, who art ſeeking to overthrow the faith; by thy lying Divination. For the Devil knowes unbelief is that which keeps from entring into reſt: ſo he ſtrikes off Faith. But many are entred in, who have heard his voice, and ſuch will believe thee no longer; for thou caſts out thy flood, after ſuch as is out of thy reach. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way thou haſt, that when I tell thee of thy lies, and deceits in thy book, leſt people ſhould find them, thou ſets them to ſeek in another page, where thou haſt made ſome cover for that deceit, and not in the place in which it is ſpoken; and thus thou ſhuffles to hide thy ſelfe, leſt thou ſhould be diſcovered in plainneſs to the ſimple: Inſtance, that about the Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>Another way thou haſt, with thy Divination to turn a thing quite contrary to what I both ſpeak and intend; and this is uſuall to thee in moſt places of thy book: Inſtance thy 55. page, thou having in thy firſt book ſeemed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny any other manner of preaching, then which was left by the Apoſtles; to which I anſwer, Then you may ſpare your pains (you Steeple-houſe-Teachers) who are out of the manner, yea, and matter alſo; and with thy divina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thou turns this, that I would ſet up a new manner of teaching, of two or three years ſtanding; when both my words and end is to eſtabliſh the old way; and therefore
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115285:7"/>
deny your Idoll-worſhip, which is out of it, your preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Printing; And in ſome of theſe wayes, or ſome other ſuch like crooked way, haſt thou caſt a miſt over the truths, wherewith I have laid open thy deceits; yet canſt thou blinde none therewith, but thy own Generation, who are blinde already; and as any of them mindes the light in ſpirit (which thou ſo much oppoſeſt) they ſhall ſee thee, and thy deceit alſo. And now having a little o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened the way to all, who deſires to know the truth, that they thereby may ſee all the reſt of thy rotten Covers, I ſhall not much contend about words; but leave the truth to manifeſt it ſelfe, to all who in the principle of truth reads our books, and enquires after it; and they who will be filthy and loves deceit, in thy book, may cover them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves therewith.</p>
            <p>Thou goes on ſaying, We come to give ſome Inſtances of his falſe charges, and you mention ſome perticular things. To which I ſay, how many (that we) is thou ſpeaks on, you know not further then that there is Legions againſt the Lamb; but to that I have ſaid, I ſhall make it appear to be true, as to the true intent of thy Doctrine without the leaſt deſire to aggravate, as follows.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>As to thy ſeeking to exclude God and Chriſt, the ſpirit and light out of the world, and that he ſhould no more dwell in his people till dooms-day, and ſo on to all the reſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To which I ſay thy words are, that it cannot be properly ſaid, that in a full and abſolute ſenſe, God was, or is manifeſt in the fleſh of any naturall Son of</hi> Adam, <hi>in the time of his Mortality; where it is plain, thou excludes all Mortality, with all the time till Dooms-day: If not, let the wiſe judge: as for thy word naturall, thou hast thrust into blinde people with, it is of no force in that place, unleſs thou prove, that all men muſt be in their naturall eſtate, during the time of their Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, which indeed beſt ſuits thy end and condition; and as for the ſpirit, thou calls it as</hi> Popery, <hi>to confeſs a ſpirit within,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115285:8"/>
to open the Scriptures; and the light within thou compares to a familiar ſpirit: In another place thou ſayes, God was not, God is manifest in the fleſh: which words, not God is, is as abſolute a deny all as can be made, and ſo preaches him not onely out of the world, but out of all the Saints and thy ſelf; thou ſayſt alſo, the Word Chriſt is perſonally abſent from us, while in theſe bodies. And in another place ſpeaking of the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of God, thou ſayes in that one perſon, not in divers; and this is to deny the Father and the Son; for he that hath not the Father, hath not the Son, and he that hath not the Son hath not life; and ſo this preaches an eternall ſeparation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Creature and the Creator, and keeps God out of his dwelling-place, denies him preſent to judge, rule, and guid; and this preaches him out of the heart, and not to be manifeſt in the fleſh; and the whole is herein proved upon thee, which I have ſaid, out of thy own mouth; and whereas thou would ſhuffle out, by ſaying, thou doſt but uphold that Scripture</hi> Paul <hi>speaks to</hi> Timothy. Iſay, Paul <hi>ſayes no ſuch words, as that God is not manifeſt in fleſh, that's thy own, therewith to deny God in the fleſh; for</hi> Paul <hi>ſaith, Great is the Myſtery, and ſpeaks of what</hi> Timothy <hi>ſhould wait for then in him, that ſo by God manifeſt in him, he might know how to behave himſelf in the Church of the living God, the Pillar, and ground of truth; which Church was in God, and God in them, who did dwell in them, and walk in them; and they knew that what God was in Chriſt, he was in them, as they had received Chriſt, according to theſe Scriptures,</hi> John 14. 20, 21. 23. John 17. 23. <hi>and they knew that they was the Temples of God: which Temples was holy, in which God was known and manifeſt, to dwell and walk.</hi> 1 Cor. 3. 16, 17. 2 Cor. 6. 16. <hi>And if any had not the Father, and the Son in them, they was warned, Nnot to receive them into their houſes,</hi> 2 John 9. 10.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:115285:8"/>
And therefore they was to try all Antichriſts, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed Chriſt in their fleſh, as thou doſt, and ſo all Idoll-Shepheards and Hirelings, who had not God in them, they denyed, and thoſe that was without God, they ſaw them to be in the world, and ſo the world would hear them, but them in whom God was they knew not; but as thou doſt now to envy and reproach, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4. 3, 4, 5, 6. 12, 13, 15, 16, 17. So that which I have ſaid of thee, is no ſlander, being proved out of thy own mouth, &amp; afterward contradicted by plain Scripture, and thou proved to be that Antichriſt, who art without God in the world, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying Chriſt now in the fleſh, and God alſo, and knowes not the great myſtery of God manifeſt in fleſh, which was great, and is great, though thou know it not now, no more then the blinde guides did then. And thy cover is, that that word Chriſt, is perſonally abſent from us, while we are in theſe bodies upon earth. I ſay thou may ſtop thy mouth for any knowledge thou haſt of Chriſt, perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall or ſpirituall: he was never known to the Idoll-Teachers, and Hirelings, and blinde Guides, and ſuch as preacht for gifts and rewards, ſuch never knew his perſon, nor appeanance: Had there not been a letter, we ſhould have little talk of Chriſt, or his appearance, with thy Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of Chemerims, who have alwayes put his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance into another Generation, wherein thou exceeds all thy Predeceſſors, who would binde him in Heaven, while he is, and while any man lives, which ſeeing, thou goes about to deny, I ſhall repeat thy words, which are theſe, in thy firſt book, page 36. That he remains in the Heavens, as oppoſed to the Earth, and where while he is, he is perſonally abſent from us, while we are in theſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies on Earth; and yet with the ſame ſhameleſs mouth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 4. 22.</note> am I accuſed as a lyer, for telling thou haſt limitted his perſon from the Earth till Dooms-day (as it is call'd) when thy words reaches further, even to while he is, which is as much as to ſay for ever: thou blinde Sot, wilt thou limit the Lord in Heaven, who fills Heaven and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115285:9"/>
Earth, who after he had deſcended into the lower parts of the Earth, aſcended far above all Heavens, that he might fill all things? And was not this the perſon of Chriſt, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ.</hi> 4. 9, 10. which deſcended, and aſcended, and that above all Heavens (which now filleth all things) which thou would limit in Heaven? Art not thou blinde, as to the letter it ſelfe? was he perſonally abſent from any of his dear Lambs in their ſufferings, though but once in the likeneſs of ſinful fleſh, to growe from a Child to a mans ſtate, that in himſelf alone he might work Redemption, and leave a living example of faith and obedience, tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and ſufferings, to all Generations that believe; and for that end was he lifted up, that through him all might believe, yet hath he appeared in divers forms, both before his ſufferings and ſince, <hi>Mark</hi> 16. 12. wherein he is not perſonally abſent? was he perſonally abſent from the three Children in the Furnace, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. 25? Was he perſonally abſent from <hi>John</hi> in the Ile of <hi>Patmos, Reveb.</hi> 1? Was he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally abſent from <hi>Paul,</hi> who confeſſeth his perſonall preſence, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 10? Nay thy ſelfe ſayes, page 2. of thy firſt book, that <hi>Paul</hi> with his bodily eyes, did behold the perſon of Chriſt, after his aſſcention; and this thou could make uſe on in thy diſpute, to plead againſt any immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Call from God; and now thou would limit him to a place while he is: Ceaſe thy Imaginations about the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Chriſt, the Serpent is as blinde about the perſon of Chriſt, as he was about the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> yet will he be diſputing to ſee if he can get in. Chriſt is revealed in the light; whoſe perſon is before the world was, and by whom the world was made, which light, thou calls a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar Spirit, as thy Fathers called him <hi>Beelzebub:</hi> ſo much knowes the carnall Imaginations of his perſon, or his light, wherein he leads out of the world to reveal his perſon to them that follow it: Is not Chriſt whereever the right hand of God is, though the blinde ſee him not? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 15. 16, 17.</note> was not the perſon of Chriſt with him, when he made the World, and by him he made it? was not he at the right hand
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115285:9"/>
of God in <hi>Davids</hi> time, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. 1. And is not he at the right hand of God in the New Creation? And is not be, in Chriſt, reconciling the world unto himſelf, whereby they become of his fleſh, and his bone? Was it not the perſon of Chriſt that came in amongſt his Diſciples, the doors being ſhut? And was it not the perſon of Chriſt that ſaid he would come again to them, though he had yet to aſcend? Which, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. 18, 23.</note> till then, the work he had to do was not wholly done; and wilt thou now bind him as a man in a Chair, who fills Heaven and Earth; yea, who is fat above all Heavens: yea, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 10.</note> where ever the right hand of God reaches, he is there; and without him (preſent) he doth nothing. Ceaſe, vain man, thou knows not whom thou would limit, who limits the word to be perſonally abſent from Believers: All the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils in Hell cannot limit him abſent, from his Lambs, in their greateſt ſtraits; who, though he be to be preacht in Heaven, yet is he not to be limited from the Earth, whom the Heaven of Heavens cannot contain, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 9, 10. Nor doth that place, <hi>Act.</hi> the 3. limit him, though it ſay the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens muſt receive him (which the world will not) but ſaith, upon their repentance, God will ſend him, whom the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens hath received: As in many other places, his appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is promiſed, waiting for, and received, as he is in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, not in imagination; and in this book thou denies him, as Mediator to be in Man, becauſe the Letter ſayes, between God and Man; thou ſayes, not in man: thou may as well ſay not in God, ſo much thou knows of him in thee: Read Chriſts words, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. 20. if he be not in God, and in Man: And whereas thou would accuſe me, for asking thee, if thou doſt not deny the Reſurrection of the Body, in ſaying, No man, as from <hi>Adam,</hi> can approach, or ſee the Lords Throne in Heaven, I ſay, had I not good ground to ask queſtion; yea, and rebuke that Lie alſo, as I did, telling thee, <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> was men from <hi>Adam,</hi> and yet did ſee Gods Throne, and Chriſt Promiſes, to ſuch as overcome, to ſit on his Throne: And doſt thou call this a ſlander to tell thee of it? then keep in thy falſe doctrine, if thou would not hear it reproved; and think not to hide thee under <hi>Johns</hi> words, which ſaith, <hi>No man hath ſeen God: for John</hi> ſaith, <hi>The onely begotten Son hath
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115285:10"/>
revealed him: John</hi> did not ſpeak theſe words, to deny the ſight of God and ſo make himſelf a lyar, who had ſeen him; but to declare the true way, to come to ſee him, which is by Revelation; which thou denies, and ſo would wreſt <hi>John's</hi> words againſt what he did witneſs and declare of.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou would accuſe me, as ſlandering thee amongſt the <hi>Pariſh-Maſters:</hi> I ſaid not, that thou was a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh-Maſter,</hi> but thou art one with them, in the ſame Spirit, for gifts and rewards, though yet thou haſt not got a Parſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage ſuitable to thy will: But art thou not a Maſter-Teacher, and in their way alſo of Pariſh-Steeple-houſes; and then what wrong have I done thee, in reckoning thee amongſt Pariſh-Teachers, and Maſters alſo? But thou wants ſomething to accuſe me, that thou might make me like thy ſelf; and ſo thou ſeeks all along in thy <hi>book:</hi> Inſtance thy accuſing me, for ſaying thou tells of ſome abatement of Perſecution, &amp;c. I ſay, let any but read thy Epiſtle to the <hi>firſt book, pa. 2. line</hi> 1. and they may ſee the Lyer; and ſo in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other things, not worth mentioning after thee; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, going to prove me a Lyar, thou proves thy ſelf one: But if any, who have the leaſt meaſure of Chriſt in them, read but thy 28. and 29. pages of this laſt <hi>book</hi> of thine, they may ſee what ſpirit is in thee, as to perſecution of us; and how thou goes about with thy lies and ſlanders, to add to our ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, which one day thou ſhalt know thou ſhould not have done, rendring to us to all the world, as though it could not ſtand with the ſecurity of any <hi>Common-wealth</hi> to ſuffer us: wherein it is plainly ſeen, what ſhall become of us, if thou get power; or if ſuch as are in Power, will but give ear to what thou haſt publiſhed to them: but to the Lord we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in theſe things, and if he do ſuffer your Generation of Murderers to get power, we may read, by what hath been done, what mercy we map expect from thee, and the reſt of that Generation, who art ſhewing thy teeth, before thou have power, rendring us in as vile a manner as thou canſt, as Papiſts, and would lay the <hi>blood</hi> they have ſhed upon us, who art in the ſtate of their Papiſt-Prieſts thy ſelf, incenſing, (and in moſt notorious ſlandering too) the Earthly Powers againſt us, all thou can, by thy falſe accuſations, too many to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115285:10"/>
mention; and when thou haſt done, to cover thy ſelf, thou ſayes thou would have to have us liberty, that thou may fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deal with us with other weapons. O full of all ſubtilty! can theſe words cover thee? It hath been always known what weapons is of moſt uſe in the hands of the Idol-Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards; which Weapons thou art ſharpning before-hand in <note place="margin">There are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thee, who thinks our ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings are not great enough: but your day is coming on apace.</note> this thy <hi>book,</hi> in which thou renders us, as not fit to be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to live in any <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> heaping up thy Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions upon us, of which we are clear; and rendring the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of hundreds of innocent Ones, as evill-doers, and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying there in the bloudy cruelty acted upon many of them, ſaying, <hi>It is not ſo great as we pretend, nor as it was in the bodily and bloody Perſecution;</hi> and then would cover thy ſelf with feigned words: But the Lord who deſpiſes not the ſufferings of the <hi>Poor,</hi> ſhall find thee out, and the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Light ſees thee, and thy opening a door to Murder and Perſecution.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou (after thy uſuall manner) caſts a ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der upon me, and when thou haſt done, aggravates it again in thy ſecond <hi>book,</hi> where in thou would make people believe, that I own no ſufferings, nor ſatisfaction of Chriſt for the world, but what was in me; and much ſuch like conjur'd ſtuff, thou raiſes out of the bottomleſs Pit, and calls it my fancy, which is but thy forgery; for I know the Offering of Chriſt for the ſinne of the whole world, in his own perſon, as I have hinted in page 56. of my Anſwer, which might have ſtopt thy mouth of this Lye: but more at large in that book, called, <hi>A Salutation to the Seed of God;</hi> and divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; which all remains, as ſo many Witneſſes againſt thy falſe ſlander: Yet did I never know his Reconciliation, Sufferings, not Satisfaction, as I ought to do (but by hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fay) untill I knew Chriſt revealed in me, with his Sufferings, Satisfaction, and Reconciliation; though I could have talked much of a thing without me, as thou doſt; yet had alwayes ſuch a feeling within me, as kept me from ſuch a common road of lying, as thou delighreſt in, and doſt exerciſe as a Trade, beyond all that ever I read or heard: Surely, doſt thou think that people are all as blind, as thoſe thou haſt in gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Doſt not thou bluſh, to tell ſuch abominable Lies,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115285:11"/>
as thou doſt in thy books, that he that runs, may read rhee ſo to be. What a Lye haſt thou framed to excuſe thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (as thou rightly calls him) about lifting his Rod to have ſtruck me on the head in the yard, at your departure, which thou knows in thy heart is a lye, and ſo many people Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſſes againſt thee: Did not <hi>John Frey</hi> himſelf ſay con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it, <hi>Now is the Devil up:</hi> Whereupon <hi>Richard Farnſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> bad him go, and reprove him then: To which he ſaid, <hi>If he was called to it of God, he ſhould:</hi> And yet thou haſt co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ered over the thing, as though he was but reaching to me with his Rod, to ſpeak to me; yea, ſo ſmooth haſt thou made it, that any who knows not thy ſpirit, or ſaw the thing, would believe thee therein. Was there ever ſuch an impudent ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit? How art thou brazened in thy wickedneſs, as though thou ſhould never account for thy tongue? And when thou haſt done, being conſcious of thy deceit, and that it could not be hid, ſo many being preſent, then thou would make me the Offender, for telling of it; and ſayes, what ever it was, I am not guided by the Spirit of Chriſt, who opened not his mouth in ſuch ſufferings, &amp;c. I ſay, Chriſt opened his mouth, and told the <hi>Murderers, Lyers, Serpents,</hi> and <hi>Vipers,</hi> what they were, though there was a time when he opened not his mouth: but if the Chief Prieſts may be Judge, Jeſus is the Offendor, and <hi>Barabbas</hi> cleared; which if thou be not acting in this thing, let all that ſee that thing acted judge thereof, who hath forged a Lye, to clear him that offered the violence, and would make me the Offendor for reproving it, though I did not reſiſt him, further then with telling him, that was the nature of a Dog to de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our and murther.</p>
            <p>Alſo, take notice of thy notorious Lies in page 30. thou accuſeſt me (but falſly) to ſay, <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt bore ſinne, in that his own body that died at Jeruſalem, ſo he had born ſinnes in my body:</hi> And ere thou leaveſt that page, thou forgets that Lye, and contradicts it thy ſelf; ſaying, (this note) <hi>That I ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for diſproving what thou ſaidſt of Chriſt, having ſo born our ſins in his own body to the Tree, at that he have not left them, ſo to be born in our ſoul or bodies, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> perfected the Sacrifice in that one Offering of himſelf once for all:</hi> And as thy tongue bew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ays thee in this; ſo doth it in moſt of the reſt;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115285:11"/>
as I might ſhew, were it worthy the while, to trace the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in his crooked ways.</p>
            <p>And thou ſpeaks of the enmity being ſlain in him, I ſay, that I know, but it is alive in thee, as the venome of thy mouth doth plainly manifeſt.</p>
            <p>And thou would make people believe, that there was a time when God did not impute ſinne unto the world, and this time thou imagines to be in the time of Chriſts under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings; and thou asks me, <hi>Where do I find thoſe that have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the word of Reconciliation, called the world.</hi> I ſay, <hi>Where doſt thou find the world reconciled to God (though he be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them that come out of the world.)</hi> But on the contrary, the whole world lies in wickedneſs, and of ſuch I ſpake; And did not God impute the treſpaſſes of the Jews to them, who murdered him, which was in the time of his undertakings: ſo thou calls me blind, but it is thy ſelf. And again, I ſay, if <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. 2.</note> God impute no ſinne to the world, then no Condemnation can be to them neither then, nor now; for they are bleſſed, to whom he imputes not ſinne. And this thou ſays opens a large door of Faith: I ſay, to the worlds faith and thine it doth, who can believe your ſins are imputed to another, and not to you, though you live in them; that makes thee ſo free in thy lying, and falſe accuſing: but we know where ſin lives, and is ſerved, the world is not reconciled to God, but ſin is imputed, and your large faith will be too large for the ſtrait-way: thy hope will periſh with the world, who art not reconciled, though God be now reconciling, as he was then in the Apoſtles time; and ſome have the word of Reconciliation, which the world and thou oppoſes, and preaches perſonally abſent; and yet art telling of two Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliations, but knows not one to live in it: but preaches a diſtance from GOD, to whom the Saints are reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</p>
            <p>Thou further tells me, if I had minded the Scriptures more, and my Imaginations leſſe, I might have ſeen that Scripture, <hi>Revea</hi> 3. 8. means not of the Lambſlain; but of Beaſt-Worſhippers: To which I ſay, were I ſo blind, as to leave both the Spirit and Scripture alſo, and believe thy blind imaginations, contrary to both, then ſhould I become a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115285:12"/>
Beaſt-worſhipper like thee: this is like thy divination of that in <hi>Amos</hi> 2. 13. where thou would have the people to read, I will preſs you, inſtead of (I am preſſed) putting man inſtead of God; and here thou would put the Beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhippers inſtead of Chriſt the Lamb, and with ſuch as this thou leads blinde, when thou meets ſuch as knows no better guide, within themſelves, but to follow thy Divinations.</p>
            <p>And thou ſayſt, By his ſtripes you are healed, and yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyeth him come, and ſaith, the Scriptures rendereth his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance alwayes to all believers, in the time to come, as that which they are to be looking for all their time in this world. I ſay thou ſpeakeſt a truth, as concerning thy ſelf, and ſo take notice, thy healing is without Chriſt, and ſo deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; but why wilt thou that art without Chriſt, judge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, and belie the Scriptures; for he that believeth hath the witneſs in himſelf, and Chriſt in you the hope of glory, who is that witneſs, and he that hath not the Son, hath not life, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. 10. <hi>Col.</hi> 5. 27.</p>
            <p>And the Scripture ſaith, We know that we are of God, and we know that the Son of God is come, and hath given us an underſtanding: And, Chriſtin you, except ye be Reprobates, And, he that abideth in the Doctrine of Chriſt, hath both the Father and the Son, elſe they was not to receive them into their houſes, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. 20. 2 <hi>John</hi> 9. 10. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 5. And <hi>Paul</hi> had Chriſt revealed in him, before he was a Miniſter, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 16. and this with thee is alwayes to come; and ſo all that thou haſt proved herein, is but thy ſelf without Chriſt, healing, and being healed: like the falſe Prophets, who hath not the word in thee, and ſo ſpeakeſt of thy ſelf, and ſo art believed by all that have Chriſt in them, and fellowſhip in his ſufferings, and in his Reſurrection; and with ſuch thou art ſeen to be Reprobate, thy preaching, and healing; who art preaching Chriſt at a diſtance, from believers, which the Apoſtle preaches in them: ſo thy work is diſcovered in all thy crooked dark paths in thy book, who art putting Chriſt far from thee, and from all that will believe thee, deſtroying their faith, by telling them they muſt never ſee, nor receive him while they live, ſuch a faith as none of the Children of God ever preached; but is of him, who, (that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115285:12"/>
he may keep his houſe in peace, while people lives) cannot endure they ſhould believe the appearance of a ſtronger then himſelf whileſt they are in this world?</p>
            <p>And with thy ſubtle divination, thou goes about to make people believe, that the Apoſtles ſince, was of an inward light and ſpirit when he told, Of ſerving their bellies; and with this thou wouldſt caſt thy dirt on the light of Chriſt, and his ſpirit within his Saints, ſhewing thy beaſtly blindneſs againſt the light of Chriſt, ſhining in his dwelling place the bodies of his Saints, and brings to prove it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 18. where all may ſee thy groſſe darkneſs, and abominable wreſting the Scriptures, doth either that, or any other Scripture, ſpeak againſt minding the ſpirituall light within, or call it ſerving the belly, which thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt make it ſpeak with thy divination? be aſhamed of thy meanings, who wouldeſt wreſt the Scriptures, which all te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie of the ſpirit and light within, (by which they was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken forth,) which thou wouldeſt call ſerving the belly, to own an inward light and ſpirit: doth not the Scriptures ſay, he that believeth out of his belly, ſhall flow Rivers of living waters, <hi>John</hi> 7. 38. which how much thou knoweſt of this, or the in-dwellings of Chriſt his light or ſpirit, or how much thou loveſt it to be believed or received in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, thou haſt ſufficiently manifeſted herein, if thou hadſt ſaid no more: nor did the Apoſtle ſpeak of them that minded the light or ſpirit within; but of them that minded earthly things, minding your bellies more then the work of God, as thou and thy Companions did at the diſpute, who broke it up, becauſe it was an hour paſt dinner time; ſuch are belly Gods, and not they who minde the light or ſpirit of Chriſt within them. And let all honeſt people judge what it is, thy deceitful lips will not make the Scriptures ſpeak, who would make the ſence of the Apoſtles words, to intend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt minding a ſpirituall light within, whoſe words is of ſuch as minde earthly things: yet in this, as in all other of thy deceits, which thou darſt not plainly a vouch: thou ſo layes down the thing, as to leave thy ſelf a way to eſcape, if thou be taxed for thy falſhood, as by thy words (ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended light oppoſed to Chriſt) when any may ſee thy envy is at the light of Chriſt and his ſpirit within; for no other
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115285:13"/>
do we pretend; and this is not oppoſire to Chriſt, as he is in Heaven, but the only thing that revealeth him in ſpirit.</p>
            <p>And thou layeſt down two Reaſons, to prove thy deceits, which no Scripture will: the firſt oppoſing, that the Apoſtle did mean, Earth-worms in a groſſe and carnall ſence; and in thy ſecond thou ſayſt, they were walkers, Brethren, they had not ſuch a form of godlineſs as ſtood in talking only, but in walking alſo. In the firſt whereof, thou ſtrikeſt at the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles words, who ſaid, they minded earthly things; but thou ſayſt, not Earth-worms; and in thy ſecond, thou ſtrikes at uptight walking, yet doth neither of them prove any thing for the further then thy confuſion.</p>
            <p>And thou wouldſt prove me to be one whoſe God is my belly; and the thing thou wouldſt prove it withall is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſay the Apoſtles preached the ſpirit and light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, ſhining in their hearts, to give the knowledge of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God in the face of Jeſus; and this Treaſure they had in Earthen Veſſels; but if angred, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 6, 7. they may ſee, that inſtead of proving me one, whoſe God is my belly, thou haſt proved thy ſelf one, whoſe Father is the Devill, who ſaith, the Apoſtle ſaith no ſuch thing; but ſaith, its my ſpirit of Antichriſt: ſo let plain Scripture judge, which is good reaſon, that it ſhould be believed, before thy lying ſpirit, who goeth on to deny the ſpirit and light, to ſhine into their hearts, as though God would ſhine into their hearts, without his ſpirit and light; and ſuch dark ſtuffe thou utters, who knoweſt not his ſpirit and light, mangling thy confuſions to darken the truth, as though I had ſaid, their hearts ſhould give them the glory of God, without his light and ſpirit, when my words are with the Apoſtle, and all the Servants of God, who witneſs the light and ſpirit, to give the knowledge of God; without which, there can be no knowledge of God, which Treaſure is in the Earthen Veſſels: which words thou leaveſt out, leſt they ſhould have ſpoyled thy deſign, in perverting the words, and deceiving the ſimple. And thou makeſt much adoe in thy Book, to drive a believers light far diſtant without, as far from them, as to the place where Chriſt was crucified, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he that was crucified on the Tree, was the fountain of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115285:13"/>
Believers light, which though he be the fountain to thoſe who have him in them, yet is he known to none, but by hear-ſay, who have him not: to ſuch the fountain is ſealed, therefore doſt thou (blind) utter forth ſo much of thy folly, who imagineth a fountain without thee, but darkneſs within, which cannot comprehend the light, though in the darkneſs it ſhine; and the Devill himſelf knowes what was done upon Mount <hi>Calvary,</hi> and the wickedſt men in the Nation, as well as thee, who haſt it not in thee: ſo you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in a Tradition, who have not the Revelation. And thou makes a babling to blinde people with, as that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle preached not the Earthen Veſſels, or themſelves. I ſay thoſe are thy own words; for none elſe I know, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends them, or mentions them; but the moſt of thy buſtling in thy Book, is to wreſt my words, or to add to them thy own, and ſo ſtart a lye out of thy own boſom; and when thou haſt done, much to do thou makes to conflite it; and this pleaſeth thy fancy, as though thou hadſt done ſome great thing, when thou haſt but confuted thy ſelf, and laid open thy ſolly.</p>
            <p>And thou goeſt creeping about to make people believe, that Chriſt is not a ſpirit, but darſt not deny it, (yet as thy manner is) caſts a miſt before it, Chriſt in ſpirit being that thou ſeeks moſt to oppoſe, for nothing elſe diſcovereth the <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5, 16.</note> Devills ſeat in man; and therefore ſaid the Apoſtle, I know him no more after the fleſh, and, When they ſhall turn to the Lord, the vail ſhall be taken away: now the Lord is that ſpirit, and where the ſpirit of the Lord is, there is liberty; <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 16, 17</note> but this liberty breaketh the Devills Kingdom: therefore his Miniſters he ſets to keep people without in the letter, i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magining a thing at a diſtance, but to believe the appearance of Chriſt in ſpirit, that is death to him, and his Miniſtry; and whereas thou tells of Chriſt, being glorified in Heaven in your nature, I ſay Chriſt was never of the nature of the lyer, neither in Heaven, nor on Earth, though he was fleſh: yet it was not that which luſteth againſt the ſpirit: none knowes his fleſh nor nature, but who knowes the word in them, which thou oppoſeth, which art full of the old Leaven, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115285:14"/>
thou askeſtance a queſtion of the Scriptures ſay the ſame] ſo take thy Queſtion back, and apply it to thy ſelf.</p>
            <p>In thy firſt Book thou made an objection, Can fleſh and blood enter into the Kingdom of Heaven? and thou anſwers, No, yet the ſame fleſh and bones may, the blood being pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out and gone to which anſwer, what confuſed ſtuffe is this that proceeds from thy imaginations? Is Chriſt aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded without blood? or is it onely the blood of people that keeps the in from aſcending, which they muſt leave behinde them, taking the ſame fleſh and bones, but not the ſame blood; and in this Book thou excuſes the matter, with ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he is aſcended without material blood; and yet with the vertues of that blood. I ſay, again, hath he materiall fleſh and bones, and not materiall blood, then is he not the ſame that he was, when he was upon earth. But why doſt thou not make ſome anſwer to thy other clauſe; how people muſt do to get ſhut of their blood, ſeeing thy faith is, they cannot aſcend till their blood be poured forth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This being a new Doctrine which the Scripture doth not declare of, it ſtands in need of better grounds, then yet thou haſt laid down, if thou intends any to believe thee therein; and this is like the reſt of thy ſtuffe, out of the dark bottle, fit for ſuch a believer to receive: then grounds<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of whoſe faith are other mens words from their Imaginations, where the word of God is perſonally abſent, and know neither light, nor ſpirit of God within them.</p>
            <p>And much adoe thou makes, and many crooked wayes, thou takes, to preach <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> out of this world, and that muſt be alwayes to come, and that yet it came not from God to any, and to diſprove that which <hi>John</hi> ſpoke in <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 2. 10. (who ſaw the new <hi>Jeruſalem):</hi> thou ſayſt, that was but a Viſion, and from that thou conjureſt up a deal of thy own filth to caſt upon me, not worth mentioning after thee: but this I ſay to thee; thou muſt firſt ſee thy ſelf in <hi>Babylon</hi> yea and the ſlandeous mouth ſlopt ere thou knoweſt the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the City of God or his dwelling place: the lyars and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> are with one and now it is ſeen in the Mount of God, asking of Viſion ſeen by others; but the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115285:14"/>
ſtrong man keeping the houſe, and thou joyned with him, ſo bring forth his works, oppoſing thy ſelf an enemy of <hi>Sion,</hi> and her Children who are come, and comming to their reſt, which thou would deſtroy the faith concerning God, Chriſt, the word, their In-dwelling in the Saints, as in thy firſt Book, who would deny that the Apoſtles preached the word and faith in the hearr. And when I inſtanced that place <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 8, 9. where the Apoſtle ſaith, The word of faith is migh in the heart. In this book thou would'ſt caſt a miſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it (leaſt any ſhould look for it there) ſaying, he ſaith not, the word and faith, but the word of faith. And ſayſt thou, he ſaith not ſimply in their hearts, but nigh them in their hearts. What ſhifts is the Devil put to, to keep Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures from looking what God hath placed in their hearts; where God hath written his Law, and placed his word, a guide to all that minde it: what ſhameful ſhifts art thou put to, leſt the Devil ſhould be diſcovered in the heart, and his Kingdom fall: Is not the word and faith, where the word of faith is, if ever that Creature come to faith: or can any have either of them but in their hearts? And doth not the Apoſtle ſay, they are in their hearts, becauſe he ſaith, they are nigh them in their hearts? But from the word [nigh] if thy divination fail not, thou wilt attempt to preach them clear out of the heart: ſo that which the Apoſtle ſaith nigh in the heart, (by thy will) muſt never come near the heart, but would put word and faith as far off, as thou haſt put Grace and Light, who ſaith, The Grace of God that bringeth ſalvation, teacheth not to look to any light within for direction. And as thou dealeſt concerning God, Chriſt, The word, Faith and light, ſo doſt thou with the City of the living God, being blinde thy ſelf, would keep all at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from others: ſuch are thy Viſions, ſuch as thy Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations: But ſeeing thou would put that <hi>Jeruſalem John</hi> ſaw out of the expectations of any whileſt the world ſtands, Read <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 22. And judge if thou canſt, of that Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> whether that was a Viſion alſo; and whether the Apoſtle ſpoke truth, when he ſaid, the <hi>Hebrews</hi> was come to the City of the living God, to the Heavenly <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115285:15"/>
ſalem;</hi> but they had denyed <hi>Babels</hi> Builders, and the Idoll-Prieſts, and their Idoll-worſhip, elſe could not they have ſeen an entrance into <hi>Sion,</hi> a City which thou haſt ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cleared thy ſelf to be ignorant of. And thou askeſt, where did <hi>[James]</hi> read of its being taken away, after its comming down from Heaven, I ſay in thee, I read it and thy Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whoſe work is to deny it preſent: I need go no further for proof, then thy own Books; As for the reſt of thy heap of confuſion, thy lies, thy ſlanders, and thy threatnings, be they to thy ſelf, for me they touch not; but ſeeing thou denyeſt <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> what City was that the <hi>Epheſians</hi> was Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens of with the Saints; which was builded upon the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Apoſtles and Prophers, Jeſus Chriſt himſelf being the chief Corner-ſtone, in whom they was builded a habitation of God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 19. 20, 21, 22. was not this the City of the living God, the new <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> but this makes ill for thy Doctrine, whoſe work is to preach God out of his people; yet when thou writeſt again, let us ſee what a ſhift the Serpent hath to avoid this; for he muſt be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in all his holes, and thou canſt not hide him. Yet didſt thou but declare thy own experience, I ſhould not contend with thee; knowing thou canſt declare no more of God, his word, his light, his faith, his dwelling place, then thou knoweſt; But ſeeing thou goes about to limit God out of his dwelling in the hearts of his people; in faithfulneſs to God, and love to ſouls, I can do no leſſe then bear teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny againſt thee, and thy work, which is contrary to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt, who preached reconciliation to God, and God in his people; but thou preaches diviſion and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and thy work is againſt any believing reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>And becauſe I tell thee of thy ſhuffling, in thy Anſwer to thy third Query, which asks Where the Covenant of God is (having reſpect to the manifeſtation of it to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) for ſo is the intent of the Query: And becauſe I tell thee thou ſhuffles and anſwers not to the Queſtion, thou tells me therein, I have crodden underſoot the Son of God, and put him to open ſhame; and that there is no more ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115285:15"/>
for ſin: I ſay it is thy deceit I tread upon, and puts to open ſhame, which is for open ſhame before the Son of God, who is the Sacrifice, and remains a Witneſs againſt thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion.</p>
            <p>The fourth Query thou pretended to anſwer, asks, What? and where that anointing is? &amp;c. And becauſe I tell thee, thou would'ſt put that to literal teaching, thou rakes up a Seal of thy own Imaginations, out of thy own boſome, to caſt upon me; as though I had ſaid, <hi>That the name of God, in Chriſt Jeſus, is no better then literal Teaching;</hi> when my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is, to reprove thee for ſetting litteral-teaching, inſtead of the Unction and Name of Chriſt; And that thou do'ſt thruſt out from the Spirit within, to the Litteral-teaching, thy Anſwer doth clearly manifeſt: though firſt to cover it with, thou makes a Confeſſion to the perſon of Chriſt, and ſuch like words, to blind the eye, leſt thy intent ſhould be ſeen: Afterward, thou comes to tell what the ſumme of this Anointing is, the ſum of the Goſpel concerning Chriſt, which thou ſaiſt is meant the things heard from the beginning, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Anointing;</hi> which after thou brings to the writings of <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy:</hi> And following it a little further, thou brings it to be the ſame to this day; which is no other but <note place="margin">For that which is not imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate from God; nor from any light and ſpirit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in muſt be litterall teachings.</note> the letter: For, ſayſt thou <hi>the preaching of it, was given by thoſe great Apoſtles, and of the ſame vertue, or quality, that ever it was, for teaching all things;</hi> and afterwards calls it the <hi>Anointing,</hi> and yet denieth any light and ſpirit within. So that all that reads thy Anſwer ſhall ſee, that I have ſpoken nothing but the truth of thee; in ſaying, Thou would thruſt it to literal teaching, and thy crooked ways cannot hide thee: But thine own words, in another place, may put the thing wholly out of doubt, where thou ſaiſt, <hi>That the grace of God that brings Salvation to all men, inſtructs them not to look to any light or ſpirit within them for direction.</hi> Here would thon thruſt out from the light and ſpirit within to literal teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contrary both to the Spirit, and the Letter alſo; for that which is in Spirit, is within, and the Letter ſaith, <hi>The anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that you have received of him abideth in you; and you need not that any man teach you, but as the ſame Anointing teacheth you of all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:115285:16"/>
Thou goes on to the fifth Query, and there thou caſts down all thy whole work, if thou do'ſt but mind what thou art there driven to, to hide thy ſelf; where thou confeſſes the <hi>Comforter</hi> that reproves the world, and leads into all truth, and reaches effectually to be in the heart, and cannot be out of it: ſo that by thy <hi>Confeſſion</hi> now, there can be no teaching out of the heart: So let any compare this with the reſt of thy <hi>books,</hi> and ſee thy confuſion, and what ſhifts thou art driven to, to and fro, like one ſtark drunk in thy Imaginations, vomiting out thy own ſhame. Is there no teaching out of the heart, and the grace of God (thou ſayes) inſtructs not to look into our ſelves, or to any Light or Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit within us for direction: What a Birth is this thou haſt brought forth into the world? How will theſe two agree? Or with what divination wilt thou reconcile them? No Teaching but in the heart, and yet not look within? But ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thou haſt confeſſed, that there can be no reproving and Teaching but in the heart, let me mind thee of it again, leſt thou forget it, it being a truth I would have thee no more to contradict it: Might not thou as well have confeſſed this long-ago, and have ſpared all thy wranglings and crooked paths thou haſt walked in, thereby to deny the Light and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit within, to be the onely Teacher, and now confeſſeth it cannot be out of the heart: So if thou own it in thy heart, thou maiſt read thy <hi>Condemnation,</hi> for oppoſing it all along in both thy <hi>books.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thou adds another Accuſation as falſe as the reſt, and that is, <hi>That I pervert most of the Scriptures I meddle with;</hi> and for inſtance, thou names that of <hi>Jer.</hi> 23. 30. which thou ſayes I do in the cloſe of my 32 page.</p>
            <p>I ſay, thou ſhameleſſe man were thou not hardened in thy wickedneſſe, paſt feeling, thou would bluſh to ſay I pervert a Scripture, where I mention none: But this is like the reſt of thy ſlanders, who can both name the Scripture, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert it thy ſelf, and then ſlander it upon me, that doth not ſo much as mention it, nor any other in that place. In thy other thou accuſed me for perverting Scriptures, where I did but quote them as they are, without a word adding; and now thou accuſeſt me, where I quote none, nor mention any at
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115285:16"/>
all, but it's impoſſible to eſcape thy tongue. It's not much to be wondered, that thou ſhould call Chriſt and his Light within, which convinceth of ſinne, nothing but a fancy, and as a familiar Spirit, as thou do'ſt. It's a ſtrange Doctrine, to thee, to know the Son of God condemning ſinne in the fleſh; and ſo it appears, when the Lyar is ſo ſtrong in thee. If thou knew any light in thee, but what is thy own fancy, the Devil would be reproved, and ſin condemned, did'ſt thou know Chriſt in the fleſh: But the Prince of the world not being udged, the Reprobate is Head, which knowes not Chriſt in thee, his Light and Spirit, which reproves the world, and guids into all truth, in whom he is known and followed: So thy <hi>Confeſſion</hi> is ſuitable to thy practice; for thou that hath not Chriſt in thee to condemn ſin, it's not like the Devil ſhould condemn what he begets: ſo thy tongue becomes without bridle, and thy heart without knowledge, that thou do'ſt evill.</p>
            <p>So deceiving, and being deceived, is thy work, even whilſt thou art telling what Chriſt did on the Croſs: Thou haſt loſt the Croſs, and to the Devil is at liberty in thee, unreproved or condemned: So not believing in the Light, thy ſelf is in the ſame <hi>Condemnation,</hi> and knows not, but is paſt feeling, being heart-blind.</p>
            <p>And thou tells of a Promiſe thou haſt made, <hi>to prove a Wolf in a ſheeps skin;</hi> and thou wilt prove it out of my Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of the righteouſneſs of God, wrought in the One Perſon of Jeſus Chriſt of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> his Sufferings, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and Aſcenſion, according to the Scriptures. And thou tells of two little words I have left out: ſo it ſeems, that to confeſs Chriſt, according to the Scripture, without two little words more, with thee is a Wolf; and with ſuch muddy, dirty ſtuff as this, not worth naming after thee, thou keeps thy promiſe, and fills thy <hi>hook.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thou ſayſt, I care not how full I make my Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of the righteouſneſſe of GOD wrought in the Death and Reſurrection of that Perſon, in that Perſonal bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: So they be not underſtood to be therein finiſhed, and need not be wrought in us. To which, I ſay that it is the thing moſt feared by thee, and him for whom thou labour'ſt,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115285:17"/>
leſt any ſhould look for the righteouſneſſe of God wrought in them: A thing which thou art little guilty of thy ſelf, out of whom ſprings the work of the Devil like a <hi>flood:</hi> yet do we know that the work of righteouſneſs is not ended and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for any Creature, ſo as to bring them to GOD, till God's righteouſneſs be wrought in them: A thing the Devil and his Miniſters, doth now, moſt of all oppoſe, though you confeſs what was done at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> yet can he keep his Kingdome in <hi>England</hi> in every heart, wherein God's righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs is not wrought: So righteouſneſs (to talk of) without, but the Devil within, is the Doctrine beſt-pleaſing to the Devil, and his Miniſters: But who are his Workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, have not ſo learned him, which knows Chriſt in us, which thou calls Antichriſtian; and thou that art without Chriſt, with the Lyar, in thee would be counted the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</p>
            <p>And further thou ſayſt, the Wolf appears under the ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skins, in my following Declaration of our Principles: To which, I ſay, I did lay down 12 particular Heads, being the chief things, which thou cunningly went about to deny in thy <hi>book,</hi> which I plainly laid down, to ſee if thou would'ſt plainly oppoſe them, as thou hadſt ſecretly ſought to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine them, that ſo the Serpent might be brought out of his holes, and diſcovered in the ſight of the ſimple, which now thou caſts thy venom at them, calling it a Wolf, but dar'ſt not deny one of them. And becauſe they may ſtand as Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes againſt thy deceit in this <hi>book,</hi> as they did in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſeeing this may come to the hands of ſome, which the other does not, I am free to ſend them to thee again, and to all the world: and do not call them Woolfs, till thou haſt ſo proved them: neither ſeek to caſt thy dirt upon them, by ſhuffling them out of their place, and ſeek to make people believe I mean another thing, then I ſpeak: ſo turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the truth into a lye, before thou dare encounter with it, that being thy old way, by which thou haſt raiſed theſe lying ſlanders in thy <hi>book,</hi> not having a ground for raiſing a ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from any thing that I have ſpoken in it, till thou haſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it one piece from another, and thruſt in thy own For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geries and Meanings, to make ſome ſhew unto people to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115285:17"/>
thy nakedneſs: without which, as it appears, thou durſt not meddle to oppoſe theſe Truths (though they be much in thy way) which are as followeth:</p>
            <p n="1">1 That the light of Chriſt, is the firſt principle that ſhews a man his <hi>condition,</hi> and leads to <hi>Chriſt the Saviour;</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, the Goſpel is hid from every Creature living; and without it, none can read with profit.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That though Chriſt Jeſus in himſelf, hath ſuffered and ſatisfied the whole will of God for all the world; yet none but who by faith in this, comes to receive a meaſure of the ſame Chriſt, in the ſame ſpirit and power, and life in them, can have redemption by him from ſin and death.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That the Word of God is ſpiritual; and who hath it, hath it in their heart; and that none who hath it not in their hearts, hath eternal life, though they may have the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as the Devil hath, to pervert to wrong ends, to plead for ſin, and tempt the ſons of God.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That none can underſtand the Scriptures, nor know the voice of Chriſt in them, but who have that ſpirit and light in them, that gave them forth to open their underſtanding to know the myſtery and life of them.</p>
            <p n="5">5 That no man knows his own heart, but who firſt owns the light of Chriſt to ſearch it, and the ſame light that ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches the heart, gives light to know God and his glory.</p>
            <p n="6">6 That the leaſt meaſure of living faith, (that is not a fancy) but ſtands in Chriſt Jeſus, is preſent power againſt all ſinne, and the greateſt power of Satan, if the Creature abide faithful in it, and run to no other helps, but mind obedience in it.</p>
            <p n="7">7 That no man can be a Miniſter of Chriſt, nor preach him truly, but who preacheth perfection, and that is the end of his Miniſtry, (which thou calleſt a Doctrine of Devils.)</p>
            <p n="8">8 That there is not one particular of the worſhip you perform in your high places, but it is added or altered from what it was, when Chriſt appointed it, and eſtabliſhed it.</p>
            <p n="9">9 That God and his Word is now manifeſt in the bodies
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115285:18"/>
of his Saints in the ſame manner, and as freely as formerly he hath been; and that there he is a ſufficient Teacher and ſhield againſt ſinne, without any other help to all, according to the meaſure of their knowledge of him preſent.</p>
            <p n="10">10 That no man can receive the things of Gods ſpirit, but who minde ſomewhat of God in them, to receive it withall.</p>
            <p n="11">11 That the leaſt meaſure of Gods ſpirit is an infallible guide, and without it no man knows Chriſt, nor can judge of any thing of God, or his truth, his Kingdom, or the way to it, or the Devil and his ſubtleties; but lies open to be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in all things, and to be led by men of corrupt minds, in whom the Devil is.</p>
            <p n="12">12 That the ground of all Errors, Sects and Opinions, Hereſies and Blaſphemies that are in the world, is, in being led from the guidance of this ſpirit; and all live in error, but who are guided by it; but none ever errs, who was guided by it alone, nor ever ſhall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe being the main things for which thou accuſes us in thy book, having wreſted them contrary to our judgment and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, thereby to darken the way of truth, more dear to me then life: to the end, that all may find it, and reſt to their ſouls, I have laid them down as plain as I can, as they are in Jeſus, in me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed without any adding or diminiſhing, as in the ſight of God: ſo when thou writes to oppoſe again, let it be plain to the people, whether thou owns or denies: ſo the difference may be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the truly wiſe in heart, and the ground of it, nad do not caſt a miſt over the truth, as in thy book, and yet dare neither own nor deny, but ſecretly bite and devour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:115285:18"/>
Here is alſo ſome of thy lies, ſent back to the Authour, and when thou proveſt them, I ſhall make my defence: till then, let them rot with the raiſer of them, which are as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 That I own my ſelf to be one of thoſe, that ſleight and reject the word of the Lord.</item>
               <item>2 That the way of lying, proud boaſting, and falſe accuſing, is the perfection of our Doctrine and Principles.</item>
               <item>3 That I own Some other ſpirit, then that in and with the Scriptures, as Gods Spirit.</item>
               <item>4 That we would preſent men perfect in themſelves, while there is nothing perfect, that ſo they may not look to the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>5 That we promiſe others liberty, freedom from ſin, glorious Conqueſt, in themſelves.</item>
               <item>6 That we count that ſin, that is looking to that Jeſus which is the very Chriſt.</item>
               <item>7 That we never make it our work, in our ſpeakings, or wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, to preach, lift up, or commend that Jeſus, as he is in that one perſonall body, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>8 That we preach not Jeſus, and the Reſurrection, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles did.</item>
               <item>9 That we make up our whole Doctrine and matter, without that which God hath laid in <hi>Zion</hi> for a foundation.</item>
               <item>10 That we magnifie not the Son of Man.</item>
               <item>11 That I aſſert nothing in my Book, of that Jeſus of <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth,</hi> in that which he hath done, <hi>&amp;c</hi>
               </item>
               <item>12 That I array Chriſt as <hi>Herod</hi> did, that I may marre his viſage, and mock at him.</item>
               <item>13 That in my Book I ſay, I am <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and that we leave no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Declarations of hope that we ſo invert not.</item>
               <item>14 That if any do preach things, according to Scripture, we revile it, as the Heathen reviled the Apoſtles, for preaching Jeſus and the Reſurrection.</item>
               <item>15 That I am a denyer of Chriſt as <hi>Judas</hi> was.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:115285:19"/>
16 That we make not <hi>Jeſus</hi> the ſum and ſubject matter of our preaching.</item>
               <item>17 That we pervert all thoſe Scriptures that ſpeak of thoſe things.</item>
               <item>18 That we are in greateſt rage againſt thoſe that plainly preach Jeſus to be the very Chriſt.</item>
               <item>19 That at the Diſpute, we did ſtoutly deſpiſe trade under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot, and marre, the viſage of the Lord.</item>
               <item>20 That I ſay I juſtifie no ſuch thing, as if any ſtrike us on the one Check, to turn the other.</item>
               <item>21 That my uſuall way of aſſerting Chriſts perſonall appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, is in my own name.</item>
               <item>22 That we contemn Authority, and deny Honour, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, civill and natural, where due.</item>
               <item>23 That Chriſt or his light in us, is darkneſſe it ſelf.</item>
               <item>24 That we uſe Chriſt in us, and the light, as a Cloak of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſneſs and pride.</item>
               <item>25 That all our ſufferings are occaſioned, as defiling the fleſh, or as evill doers.</item>
               <item>26 That we are as the Papiſts, who ſuffer much for their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples ſake.</item>
               <item>27 That our Principle leads us to follow our own ſpirit, in contempt of all Commands of ſuperiours, even ſuch as might be obeyed, in the Lord, and for his ſake.</item>
               <item>28 That our Principle leads us in contempt of all Principles of Honeſty, Juſtice, and Equity.</item>
               <item>29 That we deſire to provoke wrath in others, againſt ſuch as are in places of Truſt.</item>
               <item>30 That we deſire to ruſh our ſelves into petty ſufferings, that we may glory in them.</item>
               <item>31 That I ſaid, that as Chriſt bore ſins, in that his own body that died at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſo he had born ſins in my body.</item>
               <item>32 That I confound Chriſts forbearance of ſin done in our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, with his bearing ſin in the imputation of ſin and ſtrokes in his own body, to ſatisfie juſtice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:115285:19"/>
33 That I acknowledge no ſuch thing as Chriſts bearing ſin himſelf in his own body, in any other ſence then he may be ſaid ſtill to bear them in us.</item>
               <item>34 That I reject the Teſtimony of Chriſt, having ſuffered the juſt for the unjuſt, bearing their ſins in his body, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>35 That I fully ſignifie, that the ſufferings left behinde, are to be ſuffered in divers perſons, as propitiatory.</item>
               <item>36 That my meaning is not, that Chriſt ſo ſuffered for ſin, in that his own body prepared for him, according to Scripture.</item>
               <item>37 That I hold forth Chriſt, bearing ſin, as the propitiatory Sacrifice in us.</item>
               <item>38 That I ſay that the name of God, as in Chriſt, and in and by him declared, and as precious Oyntment powred out, is litteral teaching.</item>
               <item>39 That I deſtroy the diſtinct conſideration of the Fathers work, in laying our Iniquitles on his Son, and renders it as the work of my fancied Chriſt in the Creature.</item>
               <item>40 That I take away from you the perſonall ſufferings of Chriſt in his own body, and put in the room my imaginary or fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied Chriſt.</item>
               <item>41 That I wholly pervert every thing of Gods name that I meddle with, and turns it contrary to its ſcope and end.</item>
               <item>42 That I render the great things of the Law, to be carnall letter.</item>
               <item>43 That I reproach thee for not believing Chriſt bearing ſin in thee, as the propitiatory Sacrifice.</item>
               <item>44 That my ſence is, that Gods righteouſneſs wrought in the perſon of Chriſt, was but at moſt as a pattern, of what ſhould be wrought over again in our particular perſons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>45 That I juſtifie Chriſt, being offering himſelf daily to put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſin by the ſacrifice of himſelf.</item>
               <item>46 That we imagine that the Death and Reſurrection of our light in us is the foundation of our ſalvation.</item>
               <item>47 That I intend not the lifting up of Chriſt, but exalting my ſelf in his room.</item>
               <item>48 That my excellency lyeth in uſing craftineſſe, and hidden things of diſhoneſty.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:115285:20"/>
49 That indeed our ſpirits rejoyce in our likeneſſe to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than.</item>
               <item>50 That our inſide tends directly to marre the viſage of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>51 That I deny thy ſaying, That the word is not a Principle of men.</item>
               <item>52 That I reject the Name of God, as declared in Chriſt, and brought to light through the Goſpel, as carnall and litterall Teaching.</item>
               <item>53 That I affirm, that all that receives the word, ſuffers and ſatisfies the whole will of God for all the world in them.</item>
               <item>54 That we render the light and ſpirit to be naturally in men, as of them.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe 54 Lies have I taken out, (as I told thee in thy laſt <hi>book)</hi> from three times ſo many: theſe, with the 48. in thy laſt <hi>book,</hi> make up the number of one hundred and two. I ſhould not have troubled my ſelf to reckon them up, had not the Lyar gone about to ſeek to lay them on the truth, and ſlander the Quakers for Lyers: ſo let the Lyer be known by his fruits, who muſt be revealed by the Spirit of Truth. And when thou writeſt again, either prove what thou haſt ſaid, or ſtop thy mouth for calling Lyar for ever. And one thing more I warn thee of, that thou do'ſt not, as thou did'ſt in thy laſt <hi>book,</hi> who (becauſe I reckoned up but part of thy Lies) goes about to make people believe, I own all the reſt: For I tell thee again, there is above three times as many more, in both thy <hi>books,</hi> as falſe as theſe, which I am not guilty of, though I reckon them not here: Neither, ſay thou, I have wronged thee, in ſetting down theſe, in that I have not ſet down all thy words; for it is plain to every Reader, that I have ſet down the ſubſtance of thy ſlander, as it ſounds in the ears of the Reader, though in the moſt of them, thou haſt before-hand made thy way of eſcape, knowing them to be, what thou canſt not prove: Yea, this ſhall any ſee in thee, who are in the light, and do but obſerve thee, that in this art thou exceeds, I muſt confeſs, of all that ever I had to do
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115285:20"/>
withall, thou art the Maſter of this Craft of Lying: for, not the cleareſt truth that ever I can ſpeak, but if it be in thy way, thou wilt take into pieces, and mangle it with thy own, and turn it all into Lies, which is the Maſter-piece in thy <hi>Bookes,</hi> as I have ſhewed in particulars. And as boldly and impudently wilt thou let them fly, having but made a way to creep out and deny them, if thou be charged therewith; and if not, then thou holds it out for truth, that all is owned, that is not denied in particular: which ſhould I have done in theſe thy two <hi>Books,</hi> for one ſheet of Paper, five would not contain an Anſwer: But they being moſt of them, ſo groſs, and the Truth it ſelf ariſing againſt them a living Teſtimony in moſt parts of the Nations: It will clear it ſelf better then Paper and Ink, to the confuſion of Antichriſt, the Lyar and his Father.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
